Declan Conway

Professorial Research Fellow

Grantham Research Institute on Climate Change and the Environment, LSE

Professor Conway is an interdisciplinary researcher concentrating on the interactions between climate and society. During 2009 – 2011 he held a part-time secondment with the UK Department for International Development as a Senior Research Fellow on climate change. He is Chair of the UK Programme Executive Board of UPGro, an interdisciplinary UK Research Council research programme on *Unlocking the Potential for Groundwater in sub-Saharan Africa*. He is a member of the NERC-ESRC-DFID *Ecosystem Services for Poverty Alleviation* International Programme Advisory Committee.

Declan is a Co-editor in Chief of Global Environmental Change (Elsevier) and holds Editorial positions with; Climate Change and Development (Earthscan) and Food Security: the science, sociology and economics of food production and access to food (Springer). He was a contributing Author to the IPCC Special Report on Extremes: Chapter 3 Changes in Climate Extremes and their Impacts on the Natural Physical Environment.

His current research interests include *China's Food-Water-Energy Nexus* and *Water Security, Adaptation and Climate Change*.

Date of Birth 23.06.66 Tel: 01603 592337 d.conway@uea.ac.uk

Qualifications

1985-88	B.Sc. (Hons) Geography, Swansea University.
1988-89	MSc. Natural Resource Management, Leicester University.
1989-93	PhD, Climatic Research Unit, UEA; Climate change and the River Nile
1999	Advanced Certificate in Higher Education Practice, UEA

Employment

1993-99	Senior Research Associate, Climatic Research Unit, UEA.
1999-05	Lecturer in Natural Resources, School of Development Studies, UEA.
2005-10	Senior Lecturer in Natural Resources, School of International Development, UEA.
2010-13	Professor of Water Resources and Climate Change, UEA.
2013	Professorial Research Fellow, Grantham Research Institute on Climate Change and the Environment, LSE

Recent publications

B.A. Lankford, K. Bakker, M. Zeitoun and **D. Conway** (2013) *Water Security: Principles, Perspectives and Practices*. Earthscan Publications, London.

Deryng, D., **Conway, D.**, Ramankutty, N. and Warren, R.N. (in prep) Global crop yield response to extreme heat-stress under multiple climate change futures. **Environ. Res. Lett.**

- Tucker, J., Daoud, M., Oates, N., Few, R., **Conway, D.**, Mtisi, S., Matheson, S. (submitted) Social vulnerability in high poverty climate change hotspots: a review of the state of knowledge. **Regional Environmental Change**.
- Grainger, S. and Conway, D. (submitted) Climate change and International River Boundaries: fixed points in shifting sands. **Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews Climate Change**.
- Milman, A., Bunclark, L., **Conway, D.** and Adger, W.N. (2013) Assessment of institutional capacity to adapt to climate change in transboundary river basins. **Climatic Change**. DOI 10.1007/s10584-013-0917-y
- Yue Li, **Conway, D.**, Yanjuan Wu, Qingzhu Gao, Rothausen, S., Wei Xiong, Hui Ju and Erda Lin (2013) Rural livelihoods and climate variability in Ningxia, Northwest China. **Climatic Change.** DOI 10.1007/s10584-013-0765-9
- Goulden, M., Adger, W.N., Allison, E.H.A. and **Conway, D.** (2013) Limits to resilience from livelihood diversification and social capital in lake social-ecological systems in Uganda. **Annals Association American Geographers** 100, 1-18.
- Wei Xiong, Holman, I, Erda Lin, **Conway, D.**, Yue Li and Wenbin Wu (2012) Untangling relative contributions of recent climate and CO₂ trends to national cereal production in China. **Environ. Res. Lett.** 7 044014 (9pp) doi:10.1088/1748-9326/7/4/044014
- Pringle, P. and **Conway, D.** (2012) Voices from the frontline: the role of community-generated information in delivering climate adaptation and development objectives at project level. **Climate and Development** DOI:10.1080/17565529.2012.707608
- Wang Jinxia, Rothausen, S.G.S.A., **Conway, D.**, Lijuan Zhang, Wei Xiong, Holman, I.P. and Yumin Li (2012) China's water-energy nexus: greenhouse-gas emissions from groundwater use for agriculture. **Environ. Res. Lett.** 7. doi:10.1088/1748-9326/7/1/014035
- Li Y, **Conway, D.**, Xiong W, Gao Q, Wu Y, Wan Y, Li Y, Zhang S (2011) Effects of climate variability and change on Chinese agriculture: a review. **Climate Research** 50, 83-102. DOI: 10.3354/cr01038
- Rothausen, S.G.S.A. and **Conway, D.** (2011) Greenhouse-gas emissions from energy use in the water sector. **Nature Climate Change** 1, 210–219. DOI: 10.1038/nclimate1147
- Conway, D. (2011) Adapting climate research for development in Africa. Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews Climate Change. 2011 DOI: 10.1002/wcc.115
- **Conway, D.** and Schipper, ELF (2011) Adaptation to climate change in Africa: Challenges and opportunities identified from Ethiopia. **Global Environmental Change** 21, 227–237. doi:10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2010.07.013
- Adger, W.N., Brown, K. and **Conway, D.** (2010) Progress in Global Environmental Change Anniversary Editorial. **Global Environmental Change** 20, 1-3.
- Xiong, W., Holman, I., Jiang, J., Li, Y., Lin, E., **Conway, D.**, Xu, Y. and Hui, J. (2010) Climate change, water availability and future cereal production in China. **Journal of Agriculture, Environment and Ecosystems**, doi:10.1016/j.agee.2009.08.015
- Conway, D. Persechino, A., Ardoin-Bardin, S., Hamandawana, H., Dieulin, C. and Mahe, G. (2009) Rainfall and water resources variability in sub-Saharan Africa during the 20th century. **Journal of Hydrometeorology** 10, 41-59. doi:10.1175/2008JHM1004.1
- Xiong, W., **Conway, D.**, Jiang, J., Li, Y., Lin, E., Xu, Y. and Hui, J. (2009) Future cereal production in China: The interaction of climate change, water availability and socio-economic scenarios. **Global Environmental Change** 19, 34-44. doi:10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2008.10.006
- Goulden, M., **Conway, D**. and Persechino, A. (2009) Challenges of adaptation to climate change in transboundary river basins in Africa. **Hydrological Sciences Journal** 54, 805-828.
- Wolf, J., Brown, K. and **Conway, D**. (2009) Ecological citizenship and climate change: perceptions and practice. **Environmental Politics**, 18, 503–521. DOI: 10.1080/09644010903007377
- Allison, E. H., A. Perry, M.-C. Badjeck, W. N. Adger, K. Brown, **D. Conway**, A. Halls, G. Pilling, J. D. Reynolds and N. K. Dulvy (2009) Vulnerability of national economies to the impact of climate change on fisheries. **Fish and Fisheries.** doi:10.1111/j.1467-2979.2008.00310.x